Giulia Mazzola

she, lei, idda, ella, zij

giulia.mazzola@ncl.ac.uk | giuliamazzola.github.io | ORCID:0000-0002-7532-8671

About me

I am a usage-based linguist and my research spans Cognitive Linguistics, Sociolinguistics, and Historical Linguistics, with a focus on Romance languages. Central to my approach is the integration of speaker-focused perspectives and authentic data to bridge cognitive and sociolinguistic research. I am passionate about designing research-led curricula, and I am committed to supporting students' well-being, diversity, and work-life balance.

Work Experience

Year	Position	Institution
06/2024 - Present	Research Associate	Newcastle University
01/2023 - 06/2024	Postdoctoral Assistant	KU Leuven
10/2018 - 12/2022	PhD student	KU Leuven
11/2017 - 02/2018	Teacher of Italian as a Foreign	Volksuniversiteit
	Language	Rotterdam
10/2016 - 05/2017	Internship Foreign Language Teaching	Universiteit Leiden

Education

Year	Degree	Institution
2018 - 2022	PhD in Linguistics	KU Leuven
2015 - 2018	Research Master in Linguistics	Universiteit Leiden
2010 - 2014	Bachelor degree in Modern Languages and Literatures	Università degli studi di Palermo
	and Literatures	Patermo

Research Projects

Research Associate - How autonomous is syntax? A case study of Romance causation and perception

2024-present, Newcastle University (UK) (PI Michelle Sheehan)

International collaborator - Atlas Histórico del español

2022-2024, University of the Balearic Islands (ES) (PI Andrés Enrique-Arias)

International collaborator - Historical and typological perspectives on anticausativization

2022-2024, Università di Torino (IT) (PI Guglielmo Inglese)

PhD student - Beyond the clause: encoding and inference in clause-combining

2018-2022, KU Leuven (BE) (PI Jean-Christophe Verstraete)

Student Assistant - Haagse Spreuken

2017, Universiteit Leiden (NL), outreach project on multilingualism

Teaching

Undergraduate module of Spaanse Taalkunde III (Spanish Linguistics III)

February-June 2023 and 2024, KU Leuven - 4 ECTS

- History of the Spanish Language
- Historical Phonology
- Historical Morpho-syntax
- Philological analysis of ancient texts

Undergraduate module of Spaanse Taalkunde II (Spanish Linguistics II)

September-December 2023, KU Leuven, campus Leuven and Kortrijk - 6 ECTS each

- Morphosyntax and semantics of the contemporary Spanish verbal system
- · Analysis of contemporary texts

Undergraduate spoken practice of Spaans: taal & tekts (Spanish: language and texts) March-May 2023, KU Leuven

 Conversation practice in Spanish (second year of the undergraduate program, 2 hours per week)

Publications

Peer-reviewed publications

Journal Articles

- Mazzola, Giulia, Malte Rosemeyer, and Bert Cornillie. 2022. "Syntactic Alternations and Socio-Stylistic Constraints: The Case of Asyndetic Complementation in the History of Spanish." *Journal of Historical Sociolinguistics* 8 (2): 197–235. https://doi.org/ 10.1515/jhsl-2021-0026.
- Mazzola, Giulia, Bert Cornillie, and Malte Rosemeyer. 2022. "Asyndetic Complementation and Referential Integration in Spanish: A Diachronic Probabilistic Grammar Account." Journal of Historical Linguistics 12 (2): 194–240. https://doi.org/10.1075/jhl.20031.maz.

Edited Volumes

• Cornillie, Bert, Giulia Mazzola, and Miriam Thegel (eds.). 2023. *La Tradicionalidad Discursiva y La Lingüística de Corpus. Conceptos y Aplicaciones*. Madrid/Frankfurt a.M.: Iberoamericana Vervuert.

Book Chapters

- Mazzola, Giulia, Stefano De Pascale, and Malte Rosemeyer. 2023. "Nuevas Herramientas En La Lingüística Diacrónica: Tradiciones Discursivas y Lingüística Computacional." In La Tradicionalidad Discursiva y La Lingüística de Corpus. Conceptos y Aplicaciones, edited by Bert Cornillie, Giulia Mazzola, and Miriam Thegel, 89–118. Madrid/Frankfurt a.M.: Iberoamericana Vervuert.
- Cornillie, Bert, and Giulia Mazzola. 2021. "A Sociopragmatic Account of the Se Passive in (Pre-)Classical Spanish." In *Cognitive Sociolinguistics Revisited*, edited by Gitte Kristiansen, Karlien Franco, Stefano De Pascale, Laura Rosseel, and Weiwei Zhang, 226–41. Berlin: De Gruyter. https://doi.org/10.1515/9783110733945-019.

Non-peer-reviewed publications

 Mazzola, Giulia. 2024. Las subordinadas asindéticas en sus orígenes: un análisis de la distribución geográfica en los siglos XV y XVI. In Atlas Histórico del Español (PI Andrés Enrique-Arias). Online publication.

Work in progress

Submitted

- Inglese, Guglielmo, Eugenio Goria and Giulia Mazzola (eds.). *Diachronic and Typological Perspectives on Anticausativization*. Series: *Typological Studies in Language*. Amsterdam: John Benjamins.
- Inglese, Guglielmo, Giulia Mazzola, Eugenio Goria, Lorenzo Ferrarotti and Bert Cornillie. (forthc.) "Anticausativization and lability in Romance: a historical corpus study on Spanish and Italian". In Inglese, Guglielmo, Eugenio Goria and Giulia Mazzola (eds.), Diachronic and Typological Perspectives on Anticausativization (series Typological Studies in Language). Amsterdam: John Benjamins.
- Mazzola, Giulia, Guglielmo Inglese. Forthcoming. "Causalness, frequency, diachrony and the causal-noncausal alternation in Italian and Spanish". Corpus linguistics and linguistic theory.

In preparation

- Mazzola, Giulia. "Processing constraints in competition: a case study of syndetic and asyndetic complements in Spanish". Cognitive Linguistics
- Mazzola, Giulia, Stefano De Pascale, Malte Rosemeyer. Document-based Vector Space Models predict diffusion in language change better than genre classifications. Linguistic Vanguard

PhD Thesis

 Mazzola, Giulia. 2022. "Syndetic and Asyndetic Complementation in Spanish. A Diachronic Probabilistic Account." PhD Thesis, Leuven: KU Leuven. Download here

Talks

Invited Lectures

- Sheehan, M., Mazzola, G. (2024). How autonomous is syntax? A micro-syntactic perspective. Invited talk given at the *Meaning and Grammar Research Group*, Edinburgh University, Edinburgh.
- Mazzola, G., Sheehan, M. (2024). Causation and perception: how similar are they?
 Invited talk at *Philosophy of Linguistics Workshop*, Durham University, Durham.
- Inglese, G., Mazzola, G. (2024). "Anticausatives in Italian and Spanish across time: a corpus-based perspective". Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin, Colloquium Romanistische Linguistik, Berlin.
- Mazzola, G. (2023). "La complementación asindética en español". University of Helsinki, Helsinki.
- Mazzola, G. (2022). "Approcci descrittivi e probabilistici alla linguistica dei corpora. Esempi applicati alla complementazione in spagnolo". Università di Torino, Torino.
- Mazzola, G. (2022). "La Complementación asindética en Español: un estudio diacrónico". Freie Universität Berlin, Berlin.
- Mazzola, G. (2021). "La complementación asindética en castellano: un estudio diacrónico". Universität Regensburg, Linguistics Colloquium, Regensburg.

Selected Conference Talks

2024

- Mazzola, G. Processing constraints in competition: a case study of syndetic and asyndetic complements in Spanish. Presented at Annual meeting of the Linguistics Association of Great Britain and Northern Ireland (LAGB 2024, 27-30 August 2024), Newcastle University, Newcastle upon Tyne.
- Mazzola, G. La complementación asindética en el español (pre)clásico: ¿una influencia oriental?. Presented at the VIII Congreso Internacional de la Red CHARTA (19-21 June 2024), Universitat de les Illes Balears, Palma de Mallorca.

2023

- Inglese, G., Mazzola, G., Ferrarotti, L., Goria, E., Cornillie, B. "The anticausative alternation in Italian and Spanish: a historical corpus-based perspective". Presented at the International conference on Historical Linguistics (ICHL26), University of Heidelberg, Heidelberg.
- Inglese, G., Ferrarotti, L., Goria, E., Mazzola, G., and Cornillie, B. "The anticausative alternation in Italian and Spanish: a historical corpus-based perspective". Presented 56th Annual Meeting of the Societas Linguistica Europaea, National and Kapodistrian University of Athens, Athens.
- Mazzola, G. "Processing factors in contrast: a case study of syndetic and asyndetic complements in Spanish". Presented 56th Annual Meeting of the Societas Linguistica Europaea, National and Kapodistrian University of Athens, Athens.

Mazzola, G., De Pascale, S., Rosemeyer, M. "A Computational Approach to Detect Discourse Traditions and Register Differences. A Case Study on Historical French". Presented at the 12th Historical Sociolinguistics Network conference, Vrije Universiteit Brussel, Brussels.

2022

- Cornillie, B., Mazzola, G. "Un análisis de la pasiva en el español (pre)clásico en CODEA+2015". Presented at VI CoDiLi, Università Ca' Foscari, Venezia.
- De Pascale, S., Mazzola, G., Rosemeyer, M. "Vector Space Models for Historical Sociolinguistics: bottom-up classification of Discourse Traditions". Presented at the 11th Historical Sociolinguistics Network Conference 2022, Universidad de Murcia, Murcia.
- Mazzola, G. "Las sustantivas asindéticas en la historia del español". Presented at XII Congreso Internacional de Historia de la Lengua Española. Universidad León, León.

2021

- Mazzola, G. "Syntactic alternations and audience design: The case of asyndetic complementation in the history of Spanish (15th-18th century)". Presented at the *New ways of analyzing variation 49* (NWAV49), online.
- Mazzola, G. "From distance to immediacy? Asyndetic complementation in Classical and Present-day Spanish". Presented at the 17th International Pragmatics Association Conference, hosted by Zurich University of Applied Sciences (ZHAW), online.
- Mazzola, G., De Pascale, S. "Nuevas herramientas en la lingüística diacrónica: tradiciones discursivas y lingüística computacional". Presented at the workshop Las Tradiciones Discursivas en tiempos de lingüística cuantitativa: ¿corrección epistemológica o deconstrucción metodológica?, hosted by KU Leuven, online.
- Cornillie, B., Mazzola, G., Thegel, M. "Las Tradiciones Discursivas en tiempos de lingüística cuantitativa: ¿corrección epistemológica? ¿deconstrucción metodológica?". Presented at the workshop Las Tradiciones Discursivas en tiempos de lingüística cuantitativa: ¿corrección epistemológica o deconstrucción metodológica?, hosted by KU Leuven, online.

2020

- Mazzola, G., Cornillie, B., Rosemeyer, M., De Pascale, S. "Socio-stylistic aspects of syntactic variation: the case of Spanish asyndetic complementation (15th-18th c.)". Presented at the 53rd Annual Meeting of the Societas Linguistica Europaea (SLE), online.
- Mazzola, G., Cornillie, B., Rosemeyer, M. (2020). "La complementación asindética entre el S XV y el S XVIII: Variación socioestilística". Presented at the Jornada digital de sintaxis española Digital Workshop on Spanish Syntax, hosted by Heinrich-Heine-Universität Düsseldorf, online.

2019

- Mazzola, G., Rosemeyer, M., Cornillie, B. "La complementación asindética entre el S XV y el S XVIII: Variación socio-estilística". Presented at the *CoDiLi V*, Université libre de Bruxelles, Brussels.
- Mazzola, G., Rosemeyer, M., Cornillie, B. "The role of coreferentiality in Spanish queomission between the 15th and the 18th century". Presented at the 52nd annual meeting of the Societas Linguistica Europaea (SLE), Universität Leipzig, Leipzig.

Outreach

- Markey, M.A., Mazzola, G., Shaw, M., "The impostor's voice: Causes of and remedies for pluralistic self-doubt", in Becoming a researcher.
- Markey, M.A., Mazzola, G., Shaw, M., "D-day, or how to survive and thrive at your PhD defence", in Becoming a researcher.
- Meissl, K., Mazzola, G., Montes, M., "Bibliography chaos? Zotero your troubles away!", in Becoming a researcher.
- Mazzola, G., Kerkhof, A., "Doet m\u00e9n maah een bieahtje: het gebruik van mijn voor mij in het zeventiende-eeuwse Nederlands", Online article in Neerlandistiek- online tijdschrift voor taal- en letterkunde.

Service

Reviewing

Topics: Morphosyntax, Romance languages, Historical Linguistics, Corpus Linguistics, Inferential Statistics, Complementation, Voice-encoding strategies

Journals: - Journal of Linguistics - Isogloss - Anuari de Filología - Journal of Pragmatics - Bulletin of Hispanic studies - STUF - Language Typology and Universals

Skills and training

Language skills

Language	Level	Certificate	Competence
Italian Sicilian	Native Native		
English	Fluent	IELTS 7.0	Full professional competence (peer-reviewing, publishing and teaching)
Spanish	Fluent	DELE C1	Full professional competence (peer-reviewing, publishing and teaching)
Dutch	Intermediate	ITNA B2	Full proficiency in informal settings, limited working competence
French	Basic	DELF A2	Elementary active competence in informal settings, high competence in reading and listening

Technical skills

Category	Туре
Programming language	R (advanced), Python and HTML (basic)
Document authoring tools	Rmarkdown, Quarto, LateX, Obsidian, MS Word
Data management and control	Git, GitHub
Bibliography management	Zotero, Mendley, BibTeX
Teaching and learning platforms	Blackboard, Canvas, Microsoft Teams
Linguistics software	ELAN, Praat, AntConc
Productivity tools	MS Office Suite, Slack, Google Workspace

Additional Training

- LOT Summer School Utrecht 2016
- LOT Winter School Nijmegen 2017
- LOT Summer School Leiden 2017
- LOT Winter School Amsterdam 2019
- Fundamental Statistics KU Leuven 2019
- Advanced R Programming KU Leuven 2020
- Web Development Workshop Newcastle 2024